Preliminary Guide to the Robert Lee Flowers Records, 1891 - 1968
Duke University. University Archives
Robert Lee Flowers records 1891 - 1968
Flowers, Robert Lee. Duke University. President Duke University. Office of the Vice President
22.5 linear feet Extent: 21,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Robert Lee Flowers, born in 1870, spent his entire professional career at Duke University. From 1891 to 1951, Flowers served in a variety of capacities, including professor (1891-1924), vice president of the business division (1925-1941), president (1941-1948), and chancellor (1948-1951). Types of material in the collection include correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, bound volumes, and other printed material. Major subjects include higher education in the United States, the role of universities during World War II, the assistance of displaced scholars during World War II, the Methodist Episcopal Church, and organizations in which Flowers served, including the Duke Endowment, the Durham Chamber of Commerce, the Durham and Southern Railway Company, Greensboro College, North Carolina Central University, the Methodist Orphanage, the Oxford Orphanage, and the Lincoln Hospital. Major correspondents include William Hayes Ackland, George Garland Allen, Alexander Boyd Andrews, John Fletcher Bruton, Homer Hasenlue Dubs, Benjamin Newton Duke, William Washington Flowers, Allen Howard Godbey, Edward R. Murrow, Edward Hines Page, William Robertson Perkins, Alexander Hamilton Sands, Jr., James Augustus Thomas, and Horace Trumbauer. English.
UA.03.56.0001
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Robert Lee Flowers Records were received by the University Archives as transfers in 1953 (A48-309), 1964 (A64-62), 1971 (A71-70), 1975 (A75-114), and 1982 (A82-133).
Biographical Note
Robert Lee Flowers was born at York Collegiate Institute, Alexander County, North Carolina, on November 6, 1870, the son of George Washington and Sarah Haynes Flowers. A graduate of the U. S. Naval Academy in 1891, Flowers was first employed as an instructor in mathematics and electrical engineering when Trinity was still in Randolph County. He moved with the college to Durham in 1892. As an engineer, one of his first responsibilities was to wire the new buildings in Durham for electricity.
He served as a professor from 1891 to 1924 and as vice-president of the business division of Duke University from 1925-1941. Following the death of President Few in 1941, Flowers was named president of Duke University. In 1948, he stepped down as president and served as chancellor until 1951. Dr. Flowers was a trustee of the Duke Endowment, a director of the Durham and Southern Railway Company, a director of the Fidelity Bank of Durham, and a trustee of Greensboro College, of the Oxford Orphanage, of Lincoln Hospital, and of the North Carolina College for Negroes (now North Carolina Central University).
He married Lily Virginia Parrish on June 22, 1905. They had two daughters, Virginia and Sybil Parrish. Mrs. Flowers died on May 22, 1948. Robert Flowers died on August 24, 1951. He is buried in Maplewood Cemetery in Durham.
Collection Overview
Collection includes office files of the vice president and president of Duke University. The position of vice president included duties as secretary and treasurer. The official files consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter and other materials received or generated by these offices. The first series, Correspondence is arranged chronologically, and the second series, Subject Files alphabetically. Besides University records, the subject files include material on higher education in America, the role of colleges and universities during World War II, the committee to assist displaced scholars, Methodist Church activities and administration, and records of the various organizations for which Flowers served as a trustee. Also included in the collection is a series of several Volumes focused on Flowers, and a series of Oversize Materials from the Subject Files.
Subject Headings
Allen, George Garland, 1874-1960; Andrews, Alexander Boyd, 1873-1946; Bruton, John Fletcher; Duke, Benjamin Newton, 1855-1929; Duke Endowment; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Office of the Vice President; Duke University. President; Duke University -- Presidents; Durham (N.C.) Chamber of Commerce; Durham and Southern Railway Company; Flowers, Robert Lee; Godbey, Allen Howard, 1864-1948; Greensboro College (N.C.); Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.); Methodist Church -- North Carolina; Murrow, Edward R.; North Carolina Central University; Orphanages -- North Carolina; Oxford Orphanage (Oxford, N.C.); Perkins, William Robertson, 1875-1945; Sands, Alexander Hamilton, Jr.; Thomas, James A.; Trumbauer, Horace, 1869-1938; Universities and colleges -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Education and the war
Separated Material
President Flowers has oversize material located in map cabinet 3 including a resolution in memoriam of his death and diplomas from the Naval Academy and Trinity College.
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1891-1948
  - 1891-1924 (Box 1)
  - January-September 1925 (Box 2)
  - October 1925-June 1926 (Box 3)
  - July 1926-April 1927 (Box 4)
  - May 1927-May 1928 (Box 5)
  - June 1928-April 1929 (Box 6)
  - May 1929-August 1930 (Box 7)
  - September 1930-March 1932 (Box 8)
  - April 1932-October 1933 (Box 9)
  - November 1933-January 1935 (Box 10)
  - February 1935-August 1936 (Box 11)
  - September 1936-March 1938 (Box 12)
  - April 1938-November 1939 (Box 13)
  - December 1939-January 1941 (Box 14)
  - February-September 1941 (Box 15)
  - October 1941-February 17, 1942 (Box 16)
  - February 18, 1942-July 1942 (Box 17)
  - August-December 1942 (Box 18)
  - January-July 1943 (Box 19)
  - August 1943-February 1944 (Box 20)
  - March-September 1944 (Box 21)
  - October 1944-April 1945 (Box 22)
  - May-November 1945 (Box 23)
  - December 1945-May 1946 (Box 24)
  - June-October 1946 (Box 25)
  - November 1946-June 1947 (Box 26)
  - July 1947-March 1948 (Box 27)
  - April 1948-n.d. (Box 28)
- Subject Files
  - Ackland, William Hayes (Box 29)
  - American Association of University Professors (Box 29)
  - American Association of University Women (Box 29)
  - American Council--Institute of Pacific Relations (Box 29)
  - American Council on Education, [3 folders] (Box 29)
  - American Historical Association (Box 29)
  - Andrews, Alexander Boyd (Box 29)
  - Annual Reports to the President - Department Reports (Box 29)
  - Atlantic and North Carolina Railroad, 1933-1941 (Box 29)
  - Association of American Universities (Box 30)
  - Citizens' Emergency Committee on Nondefense Expenditures (Box 30)
  - Cowpen, C. C. (Box 30)
  - Dubs, Homer Hasenlue (Box 30)
  - Duke, James Buchanan -- Will (Box 30)
  - Duke Endowment
    - Hospital and Orphan Section, [6 folders] (Box 30)
    - Hospital and Orphan Section, [1 folder] (Box 31)
    - Report of the Secretary (Box 31)
    - Rural Church Section (Box 31)
    - Superannuate Fund, 1940-1947, [8 folders] (Box 31)
    - Superannuate Fund, 1948, [1 folder] (Box 32)
  - Duke Family (Box 32)
  - Duke Homestead -- Durham, NC (Box 32)
  - Duke Memorial, The (Box 32)
  - Duke Memorial United Methodist Church -- Durham, NC (Box 32)
  - Duke University
    - Admissions (Box 32)
    - Alumni Association (Box 32)
    - Angier B. Duke Memorial Student Loan Fund (Box 32)
    - Alumni Killed in World War II (Box 32)
    - Board of Trustees (Box 32)
    - Brown, Frank Clyde Collection of Folklore (Box 32)
    - Budget (Box 32)
    - Bus Service (Box 32)
    - Carillon (Box 32)
    - Centennial Celebration (Box 32)
    - Central Purchasing Department (Box 32)
    - Chapel (Box 32)
    - Clippings (Box 32)
    - Commencement (Box 32)
    - Debate (Box 32)
    - Committee for Investigation and Recommendation on Student... (Box 32)
    - Defense Council (Box 32)
    - Divinity School (Box 33)
    - Duke University Church (Box 33)
    - Educational Research Committee (Box 33)
    - Endowment (Box 33)
    - Engineering School (Box 33)
    - Enrollment Statistics, 1849-1937 (Box 33)
    - Exhibitions (Box 33)
    - Faculty Apartments (Box 33)
    - Faculty Committees (Box 33)
    - Faculty Housing (Box 33)
    - Faculty Publications
      - July 1941-August 1946 (Box 33)
      - July 1941-August 1949, [4 folders] (Box 33)
    - Forestry School (Box 33)
    - "Four Acres" (Box 34)
    - Fraternities and Sororities (Box 34)
    - Gifts and Bequests (Box 34)
    - Gifts and Bequests, 1936-1939 (Box 34)
    - Graduate School (Box 34)
    - Historical Material (Box 34)
    - Insurance (Box 34)
    - Insurance [Oversize Material] (Box 34)
    - King Paucus Affair (Box 34)
    - Laundry (Box 34)
    - Law School (Box 34)
    - Lawsuits (Box 34)
    - Libraries -- Flowers Collection (Box 34)
    - Libraries (Box 34)
    - Mathematics Department (Box 34)
    - School of Medicine (Box 34)
    - National Recovery Administration (Box 34)
    - Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps (Box 34)
    - Parapsychology Laboratory, [2 folders] (Box 35)
    - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 35)
    - Philosophy Department (Box 35)
    - Program of Cooperation with the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (Box 35)
    - Public Lectures, 1934-1935 (Box 35)
    - Physics Department (Box 35)
    - Quadrangle Pictures (Box 35)
    - Research Corporation (Box 35)
    - Retirement Schedule (Box 35)
    - Sabbatical Leave (Box 35)
    - South Atlantic Inter-American Workshop, 1944 (Box 35)
    - Statistics (Box 35)
    - Student Publications (Box 35)
    - Student Union (Box 35)
    - Taxes (Box 35)
    - Trinity College Historical Society (Box 36)
    - Tuition (Box 36)
    - Undergraduate Teaching Council (Box 36)
    - Veteran Students (Box 36)
    - Woman's College (Box 36)
    - Young Men's Christian Association (Box 36)
    - Duke University Press (Box 36)
  - Durham, North Carolina
    - Chamber of Commerce (Box 36)
    - Government (Box 36)
    - Young Men's Christian Association (Box 36)
  - Durham and Southern Railway (Box 36)
  - Durham County Civil Defense Council (Box 36)
  - Durham Methodist Society -- Durham, N.C. (Box 36)
  - Education, Higher (Box 36)
  - Few, William Preston (Box 36)
  - Flowers, Robert Lee
    - Letters of Congratulation on Assuming the Presidency of Duke University (Box 36)
    - Speeches and Writings (Box 37)
    - Personal Papers (Box 37)
  - Flowers, William Washington (Box 37)
  - Freak Letters (Box 37)
  - Godbey, Allen Howard, [2 folders] (Box 37)
  - Greensboro College -- Greensboro, N.C., [2 folders] (Box 37)
  - Highland Hospital -- Asheville, N.C. (Box 37)
  - Highlands Biological Research Laboratory (Box 37)
  - Kittrell College -- Kittrell, N.C. (Box 37)
  - Lake Junaluska Methodist Assembly (Box 38)
  - Lincoln Hospital -- Durham, N.C. (Box 38)
  - Livingstone College -- Salisbury, N.C. (Box 38)
  - Louisburg College -- Louisburg, N.C. (Box 38)
  - Methodist Church
    - Association of Schools and Colleges (Box 38)
    - Board of Education, [8 folders] (Box 38)
    - Board of Education, [4 folders] (Box 39)
    - North Carolina Conference, 1939-1941 (Box 39)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, South
    - Board of Education (Box 39)
    - General Board of Lay Activities (Box 39)
    - Golden Cross (Box 39)
    - Judicial Council (Box 39)
    - North Carolina Conference, 1931 (Box 39)
    - Union with Northern Church (Box 39)
    - Union with Northern Church [Oversize Material] (Box 39)
  - Methodist Orphanage -- Raleigh, N.C. (Box 40)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews (Box 40)
  - National Orphans Home -- Lexington, N.C. (Box 40)
  - National Policy Committee -- Washington, D.C. (Box 40)
  - New Duke University [Construction Costs], 1931 [Oversize Material] (Box 40)
  - Newcomen Society (Box 40)
  - North Carolina Bar Association, 1938 (Box 40)
  - North Carolina Central University -- Durham, N.C., [4 folders] (Box 40)
  - North Carolina College Conference (Box 41)
  - North Carolina Commission on Interracial Cooperation (Box 41)
  - North Carolina Division of Cooperation in Education and Race Relations (Box 41)
  - Oak Ridge Institute of Nuclear Studies (Box 41)
  - Oxford Orphanage -- Oxford, N.C., [7 folders] (Box 41)
  - Oxford Orphanage -- Oxford, N.C., [2 folders] (Box 42)
  - Page, Walter Hines (Box 42)
  - Perkins, William Robertson (Box 42)
  - Pineland College -- Salemburg, N.C. (Box 42)
  - Seeman, Ernest Albright (Box 42)
  - Simmons, Furnifold McLendel (Box 42)
  - Smith, Johnson C., University -- Charlotte, N.C. (Box 42)
  - South Atlantic Publishing Company (Box 42)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (Box 42)
  - Trinity College -- Randolph Co., N.C. -- Historical Material (Box 42)
  - United States Naval Academy -- Annapolis, M.D. (Box 42)
  - War, Students and (Box 42)
- Volumes
  - Grade Books
    - Trinity College, 1892-1893 (Box 42)
    - Trinity College, 1894 (Box 42)
  - Autograph Album of Distinguished People (Box 42)
  - Clippings and Autographs (Box 42)
  - [Letters of Tribute on Robert Flowers's 79th Birthday], 1949 (Box 42)
- Oversize Materials
  - Subject Files
    - Duke University
      - Insurance (Box 43)
    - Methodist Episcopal Church, South
      - Union with Northern Church (Box 43)
    - New Duke University [Construction Costs], 1931 (Box 43)
Related Material
[Forms part of:] Duke University President records.
University Archives. Duke University.
[Forms part of:] Duke University Office of the Vice President records.
University Archives. Duke University.
Horace Trumbauer Architectural Drawings Collection.
University Archives. Duke University.